Finding Aid for Kathleen Russell papers, 1997-2006
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Kathleen Russell papers 1997-2006
Russell, Kathleen.
0.75 linear feet
2009149 Aa 2
Papers of Kathleen Russell, former faculty advisor of Tri-Pride, Assistant Dean of Students, and director of Project YES at Eastern Michigan University; The collection documents her involvement in the campaign to pass a Non-Discrimination Ordinance in Ypsilanti, Michigan, and in establishing outreach and support organizations for GLBT youth.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Kathleen Russell (donor no. 10118 ) and came to the library on October 21, 2008.
Periodic additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Kathleen Russell was Assistant Dean of Students and director of Project YES at Eastern Michigan University (EMU). In the mid-1990s she was a member of the campus group Tri-Pride, which is an organization of social work students and professionals committed to empowering gay, lesbian, bisexual, and transgendered people (GLBT). In the Spring of 1997, Hansen's Standard Printing refused to complete Tri-Pride's printing order for raffle tickets for it's Winter fundraiser "Halt the Hate" Vigil because it was a GLBT organization. This launched Russell's involvement in the Ypsilanti Campaign for Equality, which was organized to support the passage of a city non-discrimination ordinance. Since 1997, Russell has gone on to become a leader in the EMU community, helping to organize campus-wide GLBT activities and groups, the educational outreach organization Project YES, and the Ruth Ellis Center, a center for homeless GLBT youth.
The collection consists of three series: Ypsilanti Non-Discrimination Ordinance, Eastern Michigan University GLBT Activities, and Audio-visual Materials. The strength of the collection lies in the materials Russell collected relating to the efforts to pass a non-discrimination ordinance for GLBT people in Ypsilanti, Michigan.
Subjects:
Eastern Michigan University. Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual and Transgendered Resource Center.; Eastern Michigan University--Students.; Gay men--Michigan--Ypsilanti.; Homophobia--Michigan--Ypsilanti.; Lesbians--Michigan--Ypsilanti.; Russell, Kathleen.; Transgender people--Michigan--Ypsilanti.; Ypsilanti Campaign for Equality.; Ypsilanti (Mich.)--Politics and government.
Genre Terms:
CD-ROMs.; Web sites.; Videotapes.
- Ypsilanti Non-Discrimination Ordinance
  Ypsilanti Non-Discrimination Ordinance contains materials related to the local Ypsilanti Campaign for Equality organized to promote and pass a local non-discrimination ordinance. Included in this series are several of the original raffle tickets that became the impetus for the campaign, as well as correspondence, agendas and meeting minutes, planning materials, records relating to local supporters of the ordinance, and statewide campaign training materials developed based on the success of the local Ypsilanti campaign. There is also a small amount of material related to opposition to the ordinance.
  - Agendas and Meeting Minutes, 1998 (Box 1)
  - Citizens for Community, 1997 (Box 1)
  - Challenging the Ex-Gay Movement, 1998 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1997-1998 (Box 1)
  - Local Church Support, 1997-1998 (Box 1)
  - NAACP Support, 1997-1998 (Box 1)
  - National Human Rights Campaign Materials, 1997 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1997-1998 (Box 1)
  - Ordinance Opposition Materials, 1998 (Box 1)
  - Photographs, 1997 (Box 1)
  - Planning Materials, 1997 (Box 1)
  - Raffle Tickets, 1997-1998 (Box 1)
    (original items)
  - Speeches, 1997 (Box 1)
  - Training Materials, 2001-2002 (Box 1)
  - Washtenaw Rainbow Action Project (Box 1)
  - Wimby (Box 1)
    (Welcome in my backyard)
- Eastern Michigan University GLBT Activities
  The second series, Eastern Michigan University GLBT Activities, documents the period after the Ypsilanti Campaign for Equality, when Russell became an increasingly prominent leader in EMU's GLBT community. This series includes educational materials, administrative materials for the Ruth Ellis Center, Project YES, and the Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, and Transgendered Resource Center (LGBTRC) Advisory Board, and general materials related to GLBT positive activities on campus and in the community.
  - Educational Materials Binder (Box 1)
  - Faith Communities, 2001-2005 (Box 1)
  - LGBTRC Advisory Board, 1999-2003 (Box 1)
  - Marriage Rights Materials, 2000-2004 (Box 1)
  - National and International Conference Materials, 2004-2006 (Box 1)
  - Payment Requisitions for GLBT Events, 2004 (Box 1)
  - "Pedagogies of Aids" Book Manuscript, 2000, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Project YES, 2002-2004 (Box 1)
  - Ruth Ellis Center, 1999-2002 (Box 1)
  - Project YES -- Youth for Equality and Safety (conference evaluations), 2003 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous clippings (Box 1)
    (formerly mounted on a placard)
- Audio-Visual Materials
  Audio-visual Materials, the final series, contains two VHS cassettes and two CD-ROMs. The CD-ROMs document the LGBTRC Website and a Project YES outreach presentation. The VHS cassettes relate to Russell's involvement in the push for an Ypsilanti non-discrimination ordinance.
  - LGBTRC Web Site, April 27, 2004, CD-ROM; 46.6MB) (Box 1)
  - Non-Discrimination Ordinance, VHS cassette (Box 1)
  - Traverse City Project YES Class, August 2003, CD-ROM; 16.1MB (Box 1)
  - Ypsilanti, K. Russell, May 1998, VHS cassette (Box 1)
  - Ruth Ellis Center power-point presentation, 2003, CD-R (Box 1)